THE TELL-TALE HEART by Edgar Allan Poe |
This is a LibriVox recording. |
All LibriVox recordings are in the public domain. |
For more information or to volunteer, please visit
LibriVox.org | Read by John Doyle | THE TELL
-TALE HEART by Edgar Allan Poe | True, nervous,
Very, very dreadfully nervous I had been and
am.
But why will you say that I am
mad?
The disease had sharpened my senses, Not destroyed,
not dulled them.
Above all was a sense of hearing acute.
I heard all things in the heaven and
the earth.
I heard many things in hell.
How then am I mad?
Hearken and observe how healthy, How calmly I
can tell you the whole story.
It is impossible to say how first the
idea entered my brain.
But once conceived it haunted me day and
night.
Objects there were none, passions there were none.
I loved the old man.
He had never wronged me.
He had never given me insult.
For his gold I had no desire.
I think it was his eye.
Yes, it was this.
He had the eye of a vulture, A
pale blue eye with a film over it.
Whenever it fell upon me my blood ran
cold, And so by degrees, very gradually, I
made up my mind to take the life
of the old man, And thus rid myself
of the eye forever.
Now this is the point.
You fancy me mad.
Madmen know nothing.
But you should have seen me.
You should have seen how wisely I proceeded.
With what caution, with what foresight, With what
dissimulation I went to work.
I was never kinder to the old man
than during the whole week before I killed
him.
And every night, about midnight, I turned the
latch of his door and opened it.
Oh, so gently.
And then, when I had made an opening
sufficient for my head, I put in a
dark lantern, All closed, closed, and no light
shone out.
And then I thrust in my head.
Oh, you would have laughed to see how
cunningly I thrust it in.
I moved it slowly, very, very slowly, So
that I might not disturb the old man's
sleep.
It took me an hour to place my
whole head within the opening, So far that
I could see him as he lay upon
his bed.
Would a madman have been so wise as
this?
And then, when my head was well in
the room, I undid the lantern cautiously.
Oh, so cautiously, cautiously, for the hinges creaked.
I undid it just so much that a
single thin ray fell upon the vulture eye.
And this I did for seven long nights,
Every night, just at midnight.
But I found the eye always closed, And
so it is impossible to do the work.
For it was not the old man who
vexed me, but his evil eye.
And every morning, when the day broke, I
went boldly into the chamber and spoke courageously
to him, Calling him by name in a
hearty tone, And inquiring how he had passed
the night.
So you see, he would have been a
very profound old man, Indeed, to suspect that
every night, just at twelve, I looked in
upon him while he slept.
Upon the eighth night, I was more than
usually cautious in opening the door.
A watch's minute hand moves more quickly than
did mine.
Never before that night had I felt the
extent of my own powers of my sagacity.
I could scarcely contain my feelings of triumph
to think that there I was, Opening the
door, little by little, And he not even
to dream of my secret deeds or thoughts.
I fairly chuckled at the idea, and perhaps
he heard me, For he moved on the
bed suddenly as if startled.
Now you may think that I drew back,
but no.
His room was as black as pitch with
a thick darkness, The shutters of clothes fastened
through fear of robbers, And so I knew
that he could not see the opening of
the door, And I kept pushing it on,
steadily.
Steadily I had my head in, and was
about to open the lantern, When my thumb
slipped upon the tin fastening, And the old
man sprang up in bed, crying out, Who's
there?
I kept quite still and said nothing.
For a whole hour I did not move
a muscle, And in the meantime I did
not hear him lie down.
He was sitting up in the bed, listening,
just as I have done, Night after night,
Hearkening to the death of watches and the
war.
Presently I heard a slight groan, And I
knew it was the groan of mortal terror.
It was not a groan of pain or
of grief, oh no, It was a low
stifled sound that arises from the bottom of
the soul When overcharged with awe.
I knew the sound well.
Many a night, just at midnight, When all
the world slept, It has wowed up from
my own bosom, Deepening with its dreadful echo
the terrors that distracted me.
I say I knew it well.
I knew what the old man felt, and
pitied him, Although I chuckled at heart.
I knew that he had been lying awake
ever since the first slight noise When he
had turned in the bed.
His fears had been ever since growing upon
him.
He had been trying to fancy them causeless,
but could not.
He had been saying to himself, It is
nothing but the wind in the chimney, It
is only a mouse crossing the floor, Or
it is merely a cricket which has made
a single chirp.
Yes, he had been trying to comfort himself
with these suppositions, But it found all in
vain, all in vain.
Because death, in approaching him, Had stalked with
his black shadow before him, And enveloped the
victim.
And it was the mournful influence of the
unperceived shadow That caused him to feel, Although
he neither saw nor heard, To feel the
presence of my head within the room.
When I had waited a long time, Very
patiently, without hearing him lie down, I resolved
to open a little, A very, very little
crevice in the lantern.
So I opened it.
You cannot imagine how stealthily, stealthily, Until, at
length, the simple dim ray, Like the thread
of a spider, Shot from out the crevice
and fell full upon the vulture eye.
It was open, wide, wide open, And I
grew furious as I gazed upon it.
I saw it with perfect distinctness, All a
dull blue, with a hideous veil over it
That chilled the very marrow in my bones.
But I could see nothing else of the
old man's face or person, For I had
directed the ray, as if by instinct, Precisely
upon the damned spot.
And I have not told you That what
you mistake for madness is but over-acuteness
of the sense.
Now I say, there came to my ears
a low, dull, quick sound, Such as a
watch makes when enveloped in cotton.
I knew that sound well, too.
It was the beating of the old man's
heart.
It increased my fury as the beating of
a drum Stimulates the soldier into courage.
But even yet I refrained and kept still.
I scarcely breathed.
I held the lantern motionless.
I tried how steadily I could maintain the
ray upon the eye.
Meanwhile, the hellish tattoo of the heart increased.
It grew quicker and quicker and louder and
louder every instant.
The old man's terror must have been extreme.
It grew louder, I say, louder every moment.
Do you mark me well?
I have told you that I am nervous.
So I am.
And now, at the dead hour of night,
Amid the dreadful silence of that old house,
So strange a noise as this excited me
to uncontrollable terror.
Yet for some minutes longer I refrained And
stood still.
But the beating grew louder, louder.
I thought the heart must burst.
And now a new anxiety seized me.
The sound would be heard by a neighbor.
The old man's hour had come.
With a loud yell I threw open the
lantern and leaped into the room.
He shrieked once, once only.
In an instant I dragged him to the
floor and pulled the heavy bed over him.
I then smiled gaily to find the deed
so far done.
But for many minutes the heartbeat on with
a muffled sound.
This, however, did not vex me.
It would not be heard through the wall.
At length it ceased.
The old man was dead.
I removed the bed and examined the corpse.
Yes, he was stone.
Stone dead.
I placed my hand upon the heart and
held it there many minutes.
There was no pulsation.
He was stone dead.
His eye would trouble me no more.
If still you think me mad, you will
think so no longer when I describe the
wise precaution I took for the concealment of
the body.
The night waned and I worked hastily but
in silence.
First of all I dismembered the corpse.
I cut off the head and the arms
and the legs.
I then took up three planks from the
flooring of the chamber and deposited all between
the scantlings.
I then replaced the boards so cleverly, so
cunningly, that no human eye, not even his,
could have detected anything wrong.
There was nothing to wash out, no stain
of any kind, no blood-spot, whatever.
I had been too wary for that.
A tub had caught all.
When I had made an end of these
neighbours it was four o'clock.
Still dark as midnight.
As the bell sounded the hour there came
a knocking at the street door.
I went down to open it with a
light heart, for what had I now to
fear?
There entered three men who introduced themselves with
perfect suavity as officers of the police.
A shriek had been heard by a neighbour
during the night.
Suspicion of foul play had been aroused.
Information had been lodged at the police office,
and they, the officers, had been deputed to
search the premises.
I smiled.
For what had I to fear?
I bade the gentlemen welcome.
The shriek, I said, was my own in
a dream.
The old man I mentioned was absent in
the country.
I took my visitors all over the house.
I bade them search, search well.
I led them at length to his chamber.
I showed them his treasures, secure, undisturbed.
In the enthusiasm of my confidence I brought
chairs into the room and desired them here
to rest from their fatigues, while I myself,
in the wild audacity of my perfect triumph,
placed my own seat upon the very spot
beneath which reposed the corpse of the victim.
The officers were satisfied.
My manner had convinced them.
I was singly at ease.
They sat, and while I answered cheerily, they
chatted of familiar things.
But ere long I felt myself getting pale
and wished them gone.
My head ached, and I fancied a ringing
in my ears, but still they sat and
still chatted.
The ringing became more distinct.
It continued and became more distinct.
I talked more freely to get rid of
the feeling, but it continued and gained definiteness,
until at length I found that the noise
was not within my ears.
No doubt I now grew very pale, but
I talked more fluently and with a heightened
voice, yet the sound increased, and what could
I do?
It was a low, dull, quick sound, much
such a sound as a watch makes when
enveloped in cotton.
I gasped for a breath, and yet the
officers heard it not.
I talked more quickly, more vehemently, but the
noise steadily increased.
I arose and argued about trifles in a
high key, and with violent gesticulations, but the
noise steadily increased.
Why would they not be gone?
I paced the floor to and fro with
heavy strides as if excited to fury by
the observation of the men, but the noise
steadily increased.
Oh God, what could I do?
I foamed, I raved, I swore.
I swung the chair upon which I had
been sitting and greeted it upon the boards,
but the noise arose over all and continually
increased.
It grew louder, louder, louder, and still the
men chatted pleasantly and smiled.
Was it possible they heard not?
Almighty God, no, no, they heard, they suspected,
they knew.
They were making a mockery of my horror.
This I thought, and this I think.
But anything was better than this agony.
Anything was more terrible than this derision.
I could bear those hypocritical smiles no longer.
I felt that I must scream or die,
and now again hark louder, louder, louder.
Villains, I shrieked.
Dissemble no more.
I admit the deed.
Tear up the planks here, here.
It is the beating of this hideous heart.
End of THE TAILTAIL HEART